Hey everybody, welcome
to the content video
going over section 9.2
of your textbook, Files.
We actually aren't going to get a lot of
information from this
particular section, but this
chapter does require a little bit of
introduction, I think,
before we jump into
some of the more detailed areas of
working with files. So the basic
idea I want you to get from
the textbook here is that we're
able to open files of any type in
Python. You know, you can open an
image file, a text file, a Python
file, any kind of file, a data
file, and we can do things with
them. And it becomes really powerful
being able to open up data sets
or things like that so that
we are able to actually do some
data analysis or data science. So
we're going to just go through
a couple of examples over in our
code space here of opening files
and working with them in Python.
Very first, when you're opening a
file, whether it be in your code
space on the Cloud, or if it's on
your own personal laptop or anything,
you need to give your interpreter
the exact file path to your file.
In the opening, it's just a
matter of creating a variable
to store that file. I usually
name this variable, file, and
then the method that you're
going to use is called open.
It looks just like that. within the
open function or method, we will
put the file path to our file within
quotation marks. So the file that
I want to open up is called example
.txt. I have it right here. There's
just some text in it. And I can
type out the exact file path to it.
It's going to be kind of long at
times. So it looks like it's in
data 5500 code, week five, files,
section 9.2, or sorry, example
.txt or there's usually a nice
shortcut way to do this where if
you just right click on the file
name and click on copy path you
can usually just paste it right
into your quotation marks and then
it will open that file for you
so now you're probably wondering
what happens if I just print out
the file well let's see we get
something like this so this is not
exactly what we're looking for.
As a reminder, this is what
the file looks like. So
it's just a bunch of
description on lorem ipsum text.
And I printed out this file and
I see some stuff in my output
console that is definitely not
the contents of that file. But
if we read this, we actually do
gain some interesting information.
So it says io text io wrapper
name, name of the file, mode
r encoding utf8. So if you've
done a lot of programming or
worked with a lot of files, maybe
some of that makes sense to you.
If not, that's okay. But what
I do want you to know is that
our mode is R. We're going to
talk about that in just a second.
So, this isn't really going
to do anything for us.
So, how do we actually see
the contents of our file?
And that's going to be
something called read lines,
which is a slightly different
function. So, let's say I've got
another variable, lines. I'm going
to set that equal to file.read lines.
This is another function that
takes all the contents of the file
and spits it back out to us. So
let's see what lines looks like.
Let me add some better commenting here.
Okay.
all right so check it out lines
is equal to something within a
square bracket and then we get
comma separated values so if you
were in front of me right now I'd
say what is that and you would
answer oh that's a list and I'd
say exactly right lines is a list
of the lines in the file and this
file.readlines function returns
to us a list of each of the
lines of the file. Now what if
everything in my file was just on
one line? Then we would get a list
with just one item in it and it
would be everything in my file.
Remember this function because it's
going to be more important later on.
Let me do a slightly different
example here. This is doing the exact
same thing. Now that we know we
have a list, what can we do with it?
Well we can do a lot of things but
one of the things I love to do is
iterate through my list. So for line
in lines, let's just print out the
line one at a time. It'll give us
pretty much the same thing, but oh,
let's take a look at our
output console here. So a line,
lorem ipsum is simply dummy text
of the printing and typesetting
industry. Here's the next line,
lorem ipsum has been an industry
standard dummy text ever since 1966
when designers, it was a lot of text
that survived many decades. It
was popularized thanks to sheets.
Yeah, blah, blah, blah. So we're
just looping through our list
of lines from the file and
printing them out one at a time.
Now, another important
thing when working with
files is closing the
file when we're done.
So by default, Python will close
your file at the end of your code.
so when it's done running but if
you open a file and then you're
done with it earlier on in your
algorithm you should it's best
practice to close that file as soon
as you're done accessing it so you
can do that just by saying file
.close and now your file is closed
so then if you wanted to open that
file again and do something else
to it you could do that now speaking
of opening back up the file,
we use this method or function
open to open our file. Now the open
function takes two arguments. One
is the file path and the other
is the mode in which we want to
open our file. There's three modes.
There's read, write, and append.
So if you were to open up your file
in, well I'm just going to copy
the same exact thing right here.
File equals open. If you
don't put an argument in,
Python will by default open
your file in read mode.
And it looks like this if
you were to type it out.
Quotation marks are, that opens
your file in read mode. You don't
have to put it there because
by default Python will always
open your file in read mode. Read
mode just means you can see the
contents of the file. Now what
if, I remember there's a really
important sentence I need to add
to this file like it's killing
me and I need to edit the file
alter its contents. Well then I
would open this file in write
mode which is designated by a w.
So file equals open in write mode.
Let's write a new line to the file.
I will say file.write
my favorite sentence oh dang
it I'm so bad at spelling a
sentence with an a or an e my
favorite thing to write down
is this we'll just leave it
at that and we'll slap a new
line character in there we love
that okay so file.write and
then uh I'll throw another
sentence in there file.write.
This is a new line in my file.
Another new line character.
And then we'll close the file again.
Right? So check out what happens
when I run this code now.
Nothing new gets printed out
to my console, but if I go
and look at example.txt, check
out what's in my file now.
My favorite thing to write
down is this. Wow, that's a
heart attack of a sentence.
And this is a new line in
my file. So what happened to
my lorem ipsum text? Well,
fun fact, when you open a
file in write mode, whoops,
you automatically overwrite
everything that was previously in the
file. So by reopening this file,
example.txt, in write mode, I
erased everything that was already
in it. So this kind of brings us to
our third mode of editing a file
or opening a file, append mode.
So file equals open. Let's
just paste that in there again.
This time we're going to
open it in append mode.
And let's say file.write.
One more new line.
Good, sir.
And we'll throw another one
in there for good measure.
see how my old lines are
still here that is append
mode boom all right so
now when I run my code
we should see the lines that
we wrote in there and then
we are appending new lines
to my file so So append mode,
write mode, and read mode. And I
think that's everything I wanted
to cover in this content video.
Oh, don't forget to, well, I
don't necessarily need to close
my file because I'm at the end
of my code at this point, but
still good practice too. But that
wraps up everything for this
content video. Thanks for watching.